Guide to the Douglas Crimp Papers MSS.600
Fales Library and Special Collections
Douglas Crimp Papers
1911-2019
Fales Library and Special Collections
Crimp, Douglas
Baume, Nicholas
Siegel, Marc
MSS.600
15.6 Linear Feet in 32 manuscript boxes, 1 record carton, and born-digital items in 2 shared media boxes
20.9 Gigabytes in 471 computer files
Douglas Crimp (1944-2019) was an art historian, critic, curator, teacher, photographer, and AIDS activist. Crimp taught contemporary art, art theory, dance theory, feminist theory, gay theory, and queer theory at many institutions. Crimp's work as a critic focused on postmodern art theory, and combined activism, editing, writing, and exhibition curation. His AIDS activism involved personal participation in the group ACT UP, centering AIDS in scholarly journals, and original cultural analysis that contributed to the development of queer theory. He published multiple works, including AIDS Demo Graphics, On the Museum's Ruin, and Before Pictures. The Douglas Crimp Papers (dated 1970-2019) consist of materials created and collected by Crimp documenting his life, AIDS activism, and career as an art critic, curator, and teacher in the fields of dance, film, photography, feminist theory, and queer theory. The bulk of the collection includes correspondence, scholarly articles, drafts of lectures on critical theory topics, manuscripts and drafts for published books, and notes and drafts for seminars and lectures.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open without restrictions. The collection also includes a copy of a transcript of an oral history interview of Crimp for the Archives of American Art (AAA); the interview is closed at AAA until 2030.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the estate of Douglas Crimp (Nicholas Baume, Executor, and Marc Siegel, Literary Executor) in August 2019. The accession number associated with this gift is 2020.027.
Appraisal
A list of deaccessioned books is available in the collection file.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into eight series, five of which have been further arranged into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I. Personal
Subseries IA. Family
Subseries IB. Daily Calendars
Subseries IC. Awards
Subseries ID. Photographs
Subseries IE. Activism
Series II. Correspondence
Subseries IIA. Personal
Subseries IIB. Professional
Series III. Consulting and Curatorial Work
Series IV. Teaching, Lectures, and Conferences
Subseries IVA. Teaching
Subseries IVB. Lectures and Conferences
Series V. Writing
Subseries VA. Published
Subseries VB. Unpublished
Series VI. Work by Others
Series VII. Printed Matter
Subseries VIIA. General
Subseries VIIB. Reviews
Series VIII. Subject Files
The contents of each series or subseries are arranged chronologically with the exceptions of Series II (Correspondence), which is arranged alphabetically by last name or organization name and then chronologically for more general correspondence; and Series VI and VIII, which are also arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Douglas Crimp (1944-2019) was an art historian, critic, curator, teacher, photographer, and AIDS activist. Crimp was born in Coeur d'Alene, Idaho, and studied art history at Tulane University in New Orleans. He moved to New York City in 1967, after which he worked as a curatorial assistant at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum and as an art critic for Art News and Art International. Crimp taught contemporary art, art theory, dance theory, feminist theory, gay theory, and queer theory at many institutions, including The School of Visual Arts, Sarah Lawrence College, and the University of Rochester.
Crimp's work as a critic focused on postmodern art theory, and combined activism, editing, writing, and exhibition curation. His AIDS activism involved personal participation in the group ACT UP, centering AIDS in scholarly journals, and original cultural analysis that contributed to the development of queer theory. He published multiple works, including AIDS Demo Graphics, On the Museum's Ruin, and Before Pictures, his memoir. Crimp also curated many exhibitions and wrote the corresponding catalogues, most notably, Pictures at Artists Space (1977), which helped launch the careers of artists including Sherrie Levine and Robert Longo, among others. Crimp coined the term "Pictures Generation" to define the work of artists like Longo and Levine, who appropriated images from mass culture to carry out a subversive critique. While editor of the contemporary arts journal October, he wrote articles that upended the idea of the museum as an objective space for presenting artwork. His work influenced a generation of artists, such as Cindy Sherman and Joan Jonas, by exploring the idea that a work of art is dependent on its historical and social circumstances and encouraging artists to be disruptive and revolutionary.
Sources cited:
Cowan, Sarah. "Douglas Crimp, Scholar, Curator and Art World Disrupter, Dies at 74." The New York Times. July 15, 2019. https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/15/arts/douglas-crimp-who-saw-art-through-a-social-prism-is-dead-at-74.html.
Crimp, Douglas. "Pictures." October 8 (Spring, 1979): 75-88. https://www.academia.edu/5724916/Pictures.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Materials
Oral history interview with Douglas Crimp, 2009 March 8. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Scope and Contents
The Douglas Crimp Papers (dated 1911-2019) consist of materials created and collected by Crimp documenting his life, AIDS activism, and career as an art critic, curator, and teacher in the fields of dance, film, photography, feminist theory, and queer theory. His advocacy of revolutionary advances in performance art, video, photography, painting, and sculpture is apparent in his early writing and curatorial work on such artists as Agnes Martin, Joan Jonas, Cindy Sherman, and Richard Serra, all of whom were seen as artists who were experimenting with traditional methods. Additionally, he challenged the traditional idea of a museum, which he did not see as open to experimentation; this view is evident in his collaboration with Louise Lawler for On the Museum's Ruins. When the AIDS crisis emerged in the mid-1980s, Crimp fought for the rights and visibility of people living with H.I.V.; his activism is not only reflected in his participation in different advocacy groups such as ACT UP but in his writing as well. He focused on queer theory in the 1987 special issue of October titled "AIDS: Cultural Analysis/Cultural Activism" (included in this collection in the publication, AIDS Riot: Artist Collectives Against AIDS, New York, 1987-1994) and "Getting the Warhol We Deserve: Cultural Studies and Queer Culture" (1999), about Andy Warhol, among other articles and books.
The bulk of the collection documents Crimp's career as an art critic, curator, and teacher, and includes correspondence, scholarly articles, drafts of lectures on critical theory topics, gallery invitations and announcements, and notes and drafts for seminars and lectures. Crimp's work as an editor, critic, and writer are particularly well represented through correspondence with publishers, contracts and other agreements, manuscript drafts (in both paper and digital formats), research materials, press releases, and reviews. Crimp's curatorial work is documented through loan agreements and documents used to plan exhibitions at various galleries. This collection also includes personal materials, such as weekly calendar planners from the late 1970s through the 2000s, personal correspondence, ACT UP t-shirts, and photographs (some of which are in digital formats).
Art critics; Art criticism.; Photographic criticism; Queer theory.; Feminist theory.; Photography; Art and dance; AIDS activists.; AIDS (Disease); AIDS (Disease) and art -- United States.; Arts and society; Performance art.; Art museum curators; Baume, Nicholas; Siegel, Marc; Jonas, Joan, 1936-; Lawler, Louise; Levine, Sherrie; Martin, Agnes, 1912-2004; Rainer, Yvonne, 1934-; Serra, Richard, 1938-; Sherman, Cindy; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987
- Series I. Personal, 1911-2019; 4.15 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 1 record carton; 271.6 Megabytes in 115 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of biographical and personal materials. These materials encompass his early life and family through correspondence and photographs; his daily activities through daily calendars; awards, fellowships, and grants received for his contributions to the field of art criticism and art history; his recreational activities through his photographs of vacations and friends; and his advocacy on behalf of the gay community, especially those affected by HIV and AIDS, through his involvement with Sex Panic! and ACT UP.
  - Subseries IA. Family, 1971-2019
    This subseries consists of correspondence with various family members, including Crimp's mother and brother.
    - Crimp, Mrs. Carter (Mother), 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Crimp, Gregory (Brother) and Shana, 1970-2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grandparents (Hedley and Clara), 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Crimp, Caitlin (Niece), 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mochizuki, Yoshiaki (Spouse), 2015-2019 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IB. Daily Calendars, 1977-2006
    This subseries contains daily calendars which reflect both personal and professional commitments.
    - Calendars, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Calendars, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Calendars, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Calendars, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Calendars, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Calendars, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Calendars, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Calendars, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Calendars, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Calendars, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Calendars, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Calendars, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Calendars, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Calendars, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Calendars, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Calendars, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Calendars, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Calendars, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Calendars, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Calendars, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IC. Awards, 1989-2012
    This subseries includes materials, such as correspondence, applications, and programs, related to various awards and fellowships received by Crimp.
    - Frank Jewett Mather Award, College Art Association, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rockefeller Foundation Fellowship in the Program for the Study of Sexuality, Gender, Health, and Human Rights at Columbia University, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Creative Capital/Warhol Foundation Arts Writers Grant Program, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Susan B. Anthony Institute Research Grant, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Subseries ID. Photographs, 1911-2010
    This subseries contains photographs, some negatives, and albums of Crimp's family, friends, colleagues, ACT UP events, and vacations. Presumably, many of these photographs were taken by Crimp himself.
    - Family Photographs and Photo Album, 1911-2010; cuid38918 (Box 4, Folder 8-9, E-records Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_600_ER_1)
    - Personal Photographs and Slide, circa 1960-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 7)
    - Personal Photographs, circa 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs and Negatives, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
    - Personal Photographs, circa 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Photo Album, circa 1991-19998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Personal Photographs, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Photo Album, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Personal Photographs, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs, circa 2000-2010 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Photo Album, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Personal Photographs, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Personal Photographs, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Personal Photographs, 2005-2009 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IE. Activism, circa 1990-1999
    This subseries consists of materials related to Crimp's AIDS activism. Crimp was a founding member of Sex Panic!, which was organized to oppose both mainstream political measures to control sex, and elements within the gay community who advocated same-sex marriage and the restriction of public sexual culture as solutions to the HIV crisis. The group's activities included some conventional events, such as teach-ins, summits, and lectures, and some unconventional events, such as demonstrating alongside ACT UP against the plan by the Gay Men's Health Crisis to identify seropositive patients by name in public HIV status reporting, rather than the anonymized reporting the group favored. Materials related to this group contain correspondence, flyers, editorials, memos, notes, and publicity statements. Additionally, there are various t-shirts from Crimp's participation with the group ACT UP, or AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power, which is an international, grassroots political group working to end the AIDS pandemic. His participation in various marches and rallies with ACT UP is evident in the Photographs subseries.
    - Sex Panic!, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - ACT UP (AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power) T-Shirts, circa 1990-1999 (Box 33)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1965-2019; 1.75 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
  This series consists of personal and professional correspondence (letters, postcards, and emails) with friends, colleagues, and institutions. Topics covered include artwork currently being produced by the artists themselves; professional collaborations with editors, artists, and publishers; and the mundanity of people's daily lives.
  Arrangement
  Both subseries are arranged alphabetically, followed by more general correspondence arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries IIA. Personal, 1965-2019
    The personal correspondence includes letters and emails from friends, many of with whom he also worked, such as Yvonne Rainer and Louise Lawler. Since much of this correspondence includes more intimate, personal details, it is included here. Other notable correspondents include Rosalind Krauss, Robert Longo, and Catherine Opie. In a few instances, writing of the correspondent is included, as with Marc Siegel.
    - Anderson, Dan, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Angel, Frank, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Angell, Callie, 1999-2007 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Baume, Nicholas, 1997-2004 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Belaygue, Christian, 1972-2012 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Bordowitz, Gregg, 1999-2003 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Budak, Adam, 1998-2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Chiarenza, Carl, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Cook, Richard, 1973-1985 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Copjec, Joan, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Deutsche, Rosalyn, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Dick, John and Michelle Guerrier, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Fuss, Diana, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Guillot, Bernard, 1977-2016 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Haake, Hans, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Haim, Monica, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Hurson, Michael, 1970-1977 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Jack, Damien and Bennett Gilbert, circa 1984-2000 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Kelly, Mary, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Krauss, Rosalind, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Lawler, Louise, 1985-2000 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Ligon, Glenn, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Longo, Robert, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Lucinda (Unknown Surname), circa 1970-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Martinez, Robert, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Nochlin, Linda, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Opie, Catherine, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Phillips, Christopher, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Rainer, Yvonne, 1999-2010 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Robinson, Marilynne, 1965-1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Siegel, Marc, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Solomon-Godeau, Abigail, 1974-1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Urbach, Marina, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Valverde, Isabel, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Vida, Oscar and Marilyn, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Weismann, Michael, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Weiner, Lawrence, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Werner, Hazel, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Wolff, Janet, 2000-2007 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - General, 1970-1977 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - General, 1985-1999 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - General, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - General, 2003-2019 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - General, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Subseries IIB. Professional, 1970-2019
    Professional correspondence mainly consists of letters, emails, contracts, and royalty statements with publishers, especially MIT Press, which published many of Crimp's books. Additionally, there is correspondence with authors and curators with whom Crimp worked. A few materials are in Spanish. In a few instances, writing of the correspondent is included, as with Wolfgang Ernst and Catherine Lord.
    - Akal Ediciones, 1999-2011 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1997-2001 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Andy Warhol Museum, 1999-2011 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Barber, Stephen and David L. Clark, 1999-2001 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bay Press, 1983-2001 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Beacon Press, 1994-1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Borden, Lizzie, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Clarke, Eric, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Dia Art Foundation, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Ernst, Wolfgang, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Hernández, E. J., 1997 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Institute of Fine Arts, New York University, 1970-2001 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Le Point du Jour, 2011-2018 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Lier en Boog, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Lord, Catherine, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - The MIT Press, 1988-2019 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
    - Museum of Contemporary Art (MOCA), 2015-2016 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1998-2016 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Open Society Institute, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Parachute, 2001-2005 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Phaidon Press, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Porter, Jenelle, circa 2001 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Rockefeller Residency Fellowships in the Humanities, Center for Lesbian and Gay Studies, The Graduate Center, City University of New York, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Routledge, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Tavel, Ronald, 2000-2009 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - University of California, Los Angeles, 1994-2002 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - University of Minnesota Press, 1987-2002 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Wilcox, Randal, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - General, 1974-1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - General, 1993-1998 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - General, 1999-2002 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - General, 2003-2019 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Series III. Consulting and Curatorial Work, 1970-2016; .875 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes; 82.37 Megabytes in 31 computer files
  This series reflects Crimp's work as an art consultant and curator, which focused on promoting artists who were making strides in performance art, dance, and film, such as Agnes Martin, Robert Longo, and Andy Warhol. This focus can be seen in the exhibitions Agnes Martin, Pictures, and Dia's Andy: Through the Lens of Patronage respectively. Materials consist of correspondence, memos, exhibition catalogues and annoucements, press releases, lists of artists' work, photographs of artwork, loan forms, wall text, and contracts with institutions sponsoring the exhibitions. Two exhibitions that Crimp did not curate are included here, The Pictures Generation and Pictures: Before and After, because they were inspired by Crimp's exhibition, Pictures, and reflect his influence on the art world. Additionally, some of his personal artwork was used in the exhibitions and the latter exhibition was dedicated to him. He most likely also acted as a consultant for both exhibitions. A few materials are in Spanish.
  Consulting work is arranged first, followed by curatorial work, which is arranged chronologically.
  - Consulting for Lauren Holly and Jim Carrey, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Agnes Martin, Visual Arts Gallery, 1970-1971; cuid38919 (Box 11, Folder 2, E-records Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_600_ER_2)
  - Pictures, Artists Space, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Pictures, Traveling Exhibition, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dia's Andy: Through the Lens of Patronage, Film Program, Dia: Beacon, 2004-2005 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Lives of Performers: Art, Film, Performance around 1970, Dia: Beacon, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The Pictures Generation, 1974-1984, 2008-2009; cuid38924 (E-records Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_600_ER_3)
  - Mixed Use, Manhattan, Co-Curated with Lynne Cook, Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía, 2009-2010 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Pictures, Before and After: An Exhibition for Douglas Crimp, Galerie Buchholz, 2014 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
  - Greater New York, Co-Curator, MoMA PS1, 2015-2016 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Series IV. Teaching, Lectures, and Conferences, 1992-2016; .875 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes; 65.48 Megabytes in 38 computer files
  This series contains materials related to Crimp's work as an educator, lecturer, and expert in the fields of art criticism and art history. The breadth of his knowledge, through the variety of art historical topics taught, is evident in the anonymous student evaluations from the University of Rochester and recommendation letters written on his behalf. His focus on queer theory and sexuality is reflected in his time at Columbia University and in the various lectures and conferences in which he participated.
  This series, is arranged into two subseries: (IV.A) Teaching and (IV.B) Lectures and Conferences.
  - Subseries IVA. Teaching, 1992-2016
    Teaching consists of syllabi, lecture notes, student evaluations, and administrative files (correspondence, memos, and contracts).
    - University of Rochester, Student Evaluations, 1992-2006 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - University of Rochester, Memos and Correspondence, 1993-2015 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - The Graduate Center, City University of New York, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Getty Grant Program Summer Institute, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Columbia University, Seminar Associate, 2003-2004 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - New York University, Adjunct Professor, 2008-2009 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Vassar College Seminar, 2016 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Subseries IVB. Lectures and Conferences, 2000-2015
    Lectures and Conferences contains invitations to speak; memos and correspondence; slide and image requests; images used in lectures; conference and symposia programs; and other related printed matter for Crimp's participation in academic conferences and symposia, invited lectures, and visiting artist/scholar positions.
    - Lectures and Conferences, 2000-2006; cuid38996 (Box 13, Folder 1, E-records Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_600_ER_4)
    - Lectures and Conferences, 2007-2008 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Lectures and Conferences, 2009-2015 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Visiting Artist/Scholar Positions, 2005-2015 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Series V. Writing, 1970-2016; 4.81 Linear Feet in 12 manuscript boxes; 19.71 Megabytes in 21 computer files